AJAY KUMAR SAINI | DATA ENGINEER

Location: Panipat, Haryana Telephone: 8901470846

Email: ajayksaini0806@gmail.com

LinkedIn Profile: linkedin.com/in/ajay-saini0806

Professional Profile

Dedicated and Experienced Software developer having 5 years of experience in ETL and BI solutions. Collaborative team player with ownership mentality and a track record of delivering work on time. Presently looking for a Senior Data Engineer position to enhance my skills and advancement to the next level.

Technical Proficiencies

Languages Python, Java

Technology Talend Open and Enterprise Studio [DI, Big Data]

Stack AWS

Snowflake

Database MySQL, Oracle, AS400

DevOps Docker

Versioning Tools GIT

Achievements/Certification

- Completed AWS Cloud Practitioner certification (2023).
- Winner for Technical Gameday (Hackathon) in Nissan (2023).
- Completed AZURE Fundamental (AZ900) certification (2020).
- Star of the month award (from Tata Consultancy Service) for dedication and timely delivery.

Education

- PG-DAC from CDAC Sunbeam Pune (2018-19).
- B.Tech from Kurukshetra University (2013-17).

Professional Experience

Sep 2022 - Present

 ${\bf Company: {\bf Nissan \ Digital, Trivandrum}}$

Position: Data Engineer

Outline

Building a data mart that centralizes all information related to the latest vehicle series, including body part specifications, shipment details, and vendor information. This comprehensive data repository will enable us to trace the origin of any part-related issues and pinpoint the affected vehicles for targeted recalls.

Key Responsibilities

- Ensure adherence to data quality standards and ensure delivery with highest possible quality without compromising on the timelines.
- Develop automated scripts using Python to create table in snowflakes.
- Build scalable, maintainable and testable code.
- Participating in peer code reviews and managing criteria applied during code reviews.
- Coaching and mentoring other members of the team.

Sep 2021 - Sep 2022

Company: **Cognizant Pvt.**, Gurgaon Position: **Talend Developer**

Outline

Conversion of the legacy (Mainframe based) Insurance application to a cloud-based Insurance suit, Guide Wire. The data from the legacy system is extracted and migrated to Guidewire system. Here all the insurance coverages transformations are applied before loading the data into Guidewire Policy center.

Key Responsibilities

- Developing Talend Jobs using various components related to Talend file components, processing components, system components, XML components, technical components, misc. group components, database/data warehouse components, custom code components.
- Implementation of Error Handling in jobs.
- Implementation of SCD components.
- Creating design and test case documents.
- Performing Unit and Integration testing.
- Interacting with business owner for requirement analysis for different modules to define business and functional specifications.

Jan 2019 - Sep 2021

Company: Tata Consultancy Services, Noida

Position: ETL Developer

Outline

Working as a full-time developer for a retail drugstore chain that sells prescription and on-prescription drugs and general merchandise. Retail renewal program is a program which focuses on the retail transformation with SAP at WBA.

Key Responsibilities

- Designing ETL framework for various applications related to Pricing, promotion, Zones and Deals.
- Developing custom code using JAVA for specific client requirements.
- Performing Unit and Integration testing.
- Migrated Walgreens existing ETL batches (Developed on other ETL tools like Informatica, Ab Initio) into the Talend.
- Experience using email activities to send email reports and errors.
- Developed dynamic frameworks for extraction and loading of multiple tables.